Inventory of the James Barron Papers (1) 1776-1899
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
James Barron Papers (1), 1766-1899.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 B27
2,743 items.
Correspondence and papers of Commodore James Barron relating to his career in the United States Navy, and especially relating to The Chesapeake-Leopard Affair in 1807 and to his duel with Stephen Decatur.
James Barron,; John Adams (1735-1826),; Andrew Jackson (1767-1845),; Amos Kendall (1789-1869),; Duff Green (1791-1875),; A.P. (Abel Parker) Upshur (1790-1844),; Thomas Jefferson (1743-1826),; William Oliver Stevens (1878-1955),; Jesse Duncan Elliott (1782-1845).
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 2,739 items, 04/24/1945.
Purchased: 1 item, 05/00/1969.
Purchased: 1 item, 04/00/1970.
Purchased: 1 item, 08/13/1979.
Purchased: 1 item, 09/15/1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
Commodore James Barron, born 15 September 1768 in Hampton, Virginia, died 21 April 1851 in Norfolk, served under his father, Commodore James Barron the Elder, in the Revolutionary War. He was made Captain in the Virginia Navy in 1799 and transferred to the newly formed U.S. Navy in 1803. During the War with Tripoli he commanded the U.S. Frigates New York and President when his brother, Commodore Samuel Barron, was commander of the Mediterranean Squadron. He assisted his brother in that command when the latter's health failed and returned with him to Norfolk in 1805.
Appointed Commander of the Mediterranean Squadron in 1806 with the rank of Commodore, which title he retained for the rest of his life, he sailed aboard the U.S. Chesapeake. The British ship Leopard attacked the Chesapeake when Barron refused to allow his ship to be boarded in a search for British deserters. After a brief battle, Barron surrendered and on the request of his junior officers he was brought before a Naval court martial. The command was turned over to Capt. Stephen Decatur who in the Algerian War of 1815 became a national hero. Barron was suspended from the Navy for five years in a decision criticized by many, including B. Cocke of Washington and Robert Saunders of Williamsburg.
Barron took command of the merchant ship Portia, and after several voyages was caught in a Danish port by the outbreak of the War of 1812. He attempted to get passage home but was refused it because of the Danish neutrality and remained in Copenhagen until 1819. During this period he supported himself with his inventions including a new type of mill, a rope spinning machine, a cork cutter, and a dough kneading machine. Upon his return he sought a command in the Navy and in the course of this an argument by mail with Decatur resulted in the famous duel in which Barron was seriously injured and Decatur fatally. His second in the duel, Capt. J. D. Elliott was coupled with Barron in responsibility for the duel, though perhaps unfairly.
A Naval Court of Enquiry was held in 1821 to clear the name of Barron for his absence in the War of 1812 and other charges brought against him. The decision was very noncommittal and was criticized by many, including Carter Beverley and John Taliaferro of Williamsburg.
In 1824, Barron was given the command of the Philadelphia Navy Yard, largely through the influence of his friend, General Andrew Jackson. While there he participated in the entertaining of General Lafayette when he visited the U.S.
Commodore Barron took command of the Gosport Navy Yard in 1825 where he remained until 1831 when he returned to the command of the Philadelphia Navy Yard. In 1837, he resigned that command because an officer junior to him had been appointed President of the Naval Board in Washington, and was without command until 1842. From 13 March to 30 November 1842 he commanded the Navy Asylum, a retirement home for Naval men in Philadelphia. In that position he was also in charge of the training and examination of Midshipmen for the Navy, and his advice was asked when plans were being made for organization of the Naval Academy at Annapolis in 1847. In 1845, he returned to Norfolk where he lived in retirement until his death in 1851.
During all this time he continued his interest in inventions which included a new type of pump and bellows ventilator for ships, a steam-powered battleship, a new type of dry dock, and a cylinder steam for ships developed with Amos Kendali. He was instrumental in the development of the Naval flag signal, which he first revised in 1798.
Commodore Barron supported the education of his grandson, James Barron Hope, whose early letters, a poem on Washington, and other poems are included at the end of Box 11. (See the James Barron Hope Papers for a continuation of these papers, and the Samuel Barron Papers for a chart to the genealogy of the Barron family.)
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence and papers of Commodore James Barron relating to his career in the United States Navy, and especially relating to The Chesapeake-Leopard Affair in 1807 and to his duel with Stephen Decatur. Collection includes photocopies of patents issued to Barron for his inventions and a typescript of William Oliver Stevens' An Affair of Honor, a biography of Barron. Correspondents include John Adams, Jesse Duncan Elliott, Andrew Jackson, Thomas Jefferson, Amos Kendall, Duff Green and Abel P. Upshur.
Arrangement
Arrangement
This collection is arranged mostly by date with certain subjects and materials being grouped together. These subjects include: The Leopard-Chesapeake Affair, Box-folder: 1:50-82; Undated Material, Box-folder: 12:1-35; Letters and drafts sent by James Barron, Box-folder: 12: 27-50; Manuscripts, Box-folder: 12:51-81; Accounts, Box-folder: 12:82-87; Papers connected with the inventions of James Barron, Box-folder: 14:1- 15; Pictorial Images, Box-folder: 14:16-22; and Newspaper Articles, Box: 15.
Organization
This collection is organized into fifteen series, one series for each of the fifteen boxes in this collection.
Additional Related Material
Related Material
Materials related to this collection can be found under the James Barron Hope Papers and the Samuel Barron Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Samuel Barron Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia. Samuel Barron Papers, 1793-1942.538 items.Collection number: Mss. 65 B29.
James Barron Hope Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia. James Barron Hope Papers, 1790-1965, 1847-1887.993 items.Collection number: Mss. 65 H77.
Index Terms
Persons:
Decatur, Stephen, 1779-1820.; Adams, John, 1735- 1826.; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845.; Kendall, Amos, 1789-1869.; Green, Duff, 1791- 1875.; Upshur, A. P. (Abel Parker), 1790-1844.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826.; Stevens, William Oliver, 1878-1955.; Elliott, Jesse Duncan, 1782-1845.
Subjects:
United States. Navy--History--19th century.; United States. Navy--History--Tripolitan War, 1801-1805.; Chesapeake-Leopard Affair, 1807.; Courts-martial and courts of inquiry--United States.; Dueling--Virginia.; Patents-- United States.; Subject: Inventions--History--United States.; United States--History--Tripolitan War, 1801- 1805.
Contents List
  Series 1: Box 1
- Box 1, 1776-1808, 1851, n.d. (Box-folder 1:1-82)
  Genealogical notes on the Barron Family are to be found in this box together with an autobiographical note by James Barron (1768-1851) and "Revolutionary Reminiscences" by his father, James Barron the Elder (d. 1787). (A genealogical chart of the Barron Family is to be found in the Samuel Barron Papers, Box 1, folder 1.) Naval commissions of James Barron together with his personal and naval correspondence from 1803 to 1807 are included in this first box.
  Correspondence of 1803 to 1805 covers the period from Barron's first commission through his command of the U.S. Frigates New York and President in the Mediterranean Squadron during the war with Tripoli. Several letters concern his duties as assistant to his brother, Commodore Samuel Barron, who was commander of the Squadron before relinquishing the command to Capt. John Rodgers because of ill health.
  The papers of the 1806-1807 period begin with the preparations for Barron to leave Norfolk on the U.S. Ship Chesapeake to take command of the Mediterranean Squadron with the rank of Commodore. The correspondence with Comm. Rodgers, which nearly ended in a duel but was amicably settled by the seconds is included. A description of the affair with the British warship Leopard describes the brief skirmish and the capitulation of Barron. The request of his officers for his arrest as a result of the capitulation, the passing of the command of his ship to Capt. Stephen Decatur, the preparations for the Court Martial, the testimony, and the sentence of suspension are in the material found in this box. Opinions regarding the unfairness of the sentence by B. Cocke of Washington and Robert Saunders, President of William and Mary College, and others, are included.
  - Genealogical notes beginning with "Com. Jas. Barron of the Revolutionary State Navy," n.d., 2 pages. Adr, E. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Endorsement, n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
    "Jan. 17, 1961... Note at top is Janey Hope Marr's" signed A[nne] W. Marr.
  - Genealogical notes on the Barron Family, n.d., ADr. TDr. Typed copy included. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Autobiographical notes [by James Barron], with endorsement, n.d., ADr,E. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Autobiographical notes [by James Barron], n.d., ADr. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Page from a travel journal [of James Barron], n.d., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Items concerning a memoir by Comd're Jas. Barron, 21 June 1776, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
    "Memoir of Comd're Jas. Barron," 2 pages; and a memorandum regarding the writing of such a memoir.
  - Endorsed "Comm. Barron's paper" and "Revolutionary Reminiscences," 21 June 1776., 3 pages. ACopE. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Re: naval engagements in the War, in one of which "the two Captains Barron" were involved.
  - An account attributed to John Cowper, n.d., 4 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Re: "the remarkable escape of the private armed Ship Marquis La Fayette," 1779-to 1781.
  - Agreement for the hire of the ship John by the French Legation for transportation of provisions, furniture, etc., from Norfolk to a Port in France, 21 March 1796., 3 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Commission of James Barron as a Lieutenant in the U.S. Navy, signed by John Adams, 9 March 1798., 1 page. ADS. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Commission of James Barron, Norfolk, to serve as a Lieutenant in the Navy aboard the Frigate United States under Captain John Barry, signed by James M. Henry, 13 March 1798., 1 page. ADS. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Letter - Moses Myers, Norfolk, to Comm. Barry, United States Frigate Philadelphia, 10 April 1798., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Item concerns the recommendation of Capt. James Barron, who is seeking a promotion.
  - Letter - W[illia]m Pennock, Norfolk, to Capt. James Barron, Philadelphia, 21 May 1798., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Re: Barron's new post.
  - Letter - Sam[ue]l Barron, Norfolk, to James Barron, on board the U. States, Philadelphia, 22 May 1798., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Re: ship which is being completed; Kentucky papers [for war bounty lands] sent by Mr. Saunders; and inquiry about their value.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Baltimore, to Col. Josiah Parker, Member of Congress, Philadelphia, 16 April 1800., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Item is criticizing the U.S. ship, Insurgent by stating, "... would not go to sea in her for the world... ."
  - Letter - James Barron, Hampton, to Benjamin Stoddert, Secretary of the Navy, City Washington, 5 July 1800., 1 page. ACopS. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Re: completion of the signals.
  - Letter - S.M. Merideth, Treasury of the United States, to Capt. James Barron, Norfolk, Virginia, 23 September 1800., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
    Includes a draft payment.
  - Letter - R[ober]t Smith, Navy Department, to Commodore Rich'd. Dale, of the Frigate President, 14 December 1800., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:15)
    Re: Instructions to bring the ship up the Potomac to Washington.
  - Copies of parts of correspondence between Comm're Truxton and the Secretary of the Navy, 1802-1805., ACop. (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Letter, 13 March 1802. (Box-folder 1:16)
      R[ober]t Smith writes that no Captain is available for such a secondary position aboard ship. He accepts Truxton's resignation and appoints Capt. Morris to command the Chesapeake.
    - Letter, 7 Sept. 1805. (Box-folder 1:16)
      Comm. Truxton denies that he intended to resign his commission but only meant to be relieved of the command of the Mediterranean Squadron.
  - Letter - [James Barron] to the Secretary of the Navy, 21 April 1802., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 1:17)
    Re: Comm. Dale and sailing plans.
  - Receipts issued to Capt. James Barron and Mrs Elizabeth Barron, May-August 1802., 3 items. ADS. (Box-folder 1:18)
  - "Uniform Dress of the Captains and Certain Other Officers of the United States Navy," issued by R[obert] Smith, Navy Department, 27 August 1802., 2 pages. PM. (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Account of Capt. James Barron with Ja[me]s Woodward, Norfolk, 20 [ ] 1802. (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Letter - Capt. James Barron, U.S. Frigate New York, Malta, to Capt. Samuel Barron, Hampton, Virginia, 28 January 1803., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:21)
    Re: war in the Mediterranean; expectation to sail for Tripoli; criticism of way war is carried on; Algiers and Tangiers both threatening war; his order to give up command of the New York and take command of a "much neglected and horribly disciplined" ship; message to Bainbridge, etc.
  - Letter - Reprint of letter sent to Commodore Barron on occasion of his leaving the Mediterranean Command, signed by 11 officers, 5 April 1803., 1 page. PM. (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Bill to Capt. James Barron from Mrs. Mary Chisman, 24 December 1803., 1 page. ADS. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Letter - W. Rassay, London, to James Barron, Hampton, Virginia--Forwarded, 4 March 1804., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:24)
    Re: a horse for which he wants $5,000.
  - Letter - William Eaton, Derne, The Kingdom of Tripoli, to Captain James Barron, U. States Navy, Mediterranean, 17 May 1805., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:25)
    The letter accompanied a gift of a Damascus saber.
  - Letter - Comm. Jno. Rodgers, U.S. Ship Constitution, off Tripoli, to Captn. James Barron, U. States Frigate Essex, off Tripoli, 29 May 1805., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:26)
    Re: Orders for the taking command of the President and future movements of the ship and Squadron.
  - Letter - Jno. Rodgers, U.S. Ship Constitution, off Tripoli, to Capt. James Barron, U.S. Frigate President, Malta, 2 June 1805., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:27)
    Re: Orders for the collection of the Squadron, "If the Business here is Settled."
  - Letter - A. Sinclair, the Essex, Gibraltar, to Capt. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Hampton, Virginia, 18 September 1805., 7 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:28)
    Re: affairs in the Mediterranean after James Barron left. News of Col. Lear and Comm. Rodgers at Tunis, Lear negotiating to avoid war, Rodgers continuing to fire on Tunisian vessels. News of the duplicity of Comm. Rodgers; of Lord Nelson's unsuccessful pursuit of the French; of 9 American ships at Gibraltar, prizes of the British.
  - Letter - R[ober]t Smith, Navy Department, to Capn. James Barron, Washington, 20 September 1805., ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Orders: after delivering the President to Capt. Tingey, James Barron is to prepare for the construction of a 74 gun ship at Portsmouth.
  - Copybook of Jane A. Barron, daughter of James Barron, 1805-1808., 32 pages. AVS. (Box-folder 1:30)
    Item contains 4 letters and 16 poems.
  - Letter - Maj. N. Ramsay, London and Dundee, to James Brodie and [James Barron], Hampton, Virginia, February-August 1806., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:31)
    Re: Arab horse, Selim, which was sent to America.
  - Letters - R[ober]t Smith, Navy Department, to Comm. James Barron, Hampton, Virginia, April-July 1806., 4 items. ALS. (Box-folder 1:32)
    An order to hold himself ready to sail on the frigate Chesapeake for the purpose of taking the command of the American Squadron in the Mediterranean; suspension of the orders because the Chesapeake was not ready to sail.
  - Letter - Isaac Chauncey, New York, to Captain James Barron, U.S. Navy, Hampton, Virginia, 4 May 1806., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:33)
    Felicitation on appointment to command the Mediterranean Squadron; re: a brother who was a Midshipman on the Constitution.
  - Bill to Commodore Barron for work done on his house at Mill Creek by M. T. Proby, May 1806., ADS. (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Letter - B. Cocke, Washington, to Captain James Barron, Hampton, Virginia, 29 July 1806., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:35)
    Re: the affair between Barron and Comm. Rodgers concerning which "much anxiety is excited among...your friends."
  - Letters - exchanged by Comm. John Rodgers, U.S. Frigate Essex, Capt. James Barron, U. States Navy, Hampton, Virginia, and by Franklin Wharton and Thomas Tingley, both of Washington, July 1806-March 1807., 10 letters. AlsS. (Box-folder 1:36)
    Relative to threatened duel between Barron and Rodgers; printed terms of settlement published 31 January 1807.
  - Folder 37 currently does not exist in this collection.
  - Letters - Copies of letters exchanged by Col. Franklin Wharton and Thomas Tingley in Washington, and with Commo. John Rodgers and Capt. James Barron, August 1806--March 1807., 20 letters. ACop. (Box-folder 1:38)
    Arrangements are made to meet at Havre de Grace, Maryland, for the duel of Barron and Rodgers, despite the orders of the Secretary of the Navy; news that agreement to a settlement has been reached.
  - Letter - R[ober]t Smith, Navy Department, to Capt. James Barron, Hampton, Virginia, 17 December 1806., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:39)
    Re: new orders shortly to come to Capt. Barron, until which time he "will not move from that place without special orders from me."
  - Letters - R[ober]t Smith, Navy Department, to Capt. James Barron, Hampton, Virginia, January-May 1807., 8 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:40)
    Preparations for the sailing on the Chesapeake, including a question regarding the powder which was "not fit for service" and was to be remanufactured at Malta, 23 March 1807; endorsement by James Barron, "The Chesapeake's Powder, an important paper."
  - Receipt by Elizabeth Barron for payment for a piece of land, 15 February 1807., ALS. (Box-folder 1:41)
  - Letter - A. Sinclair, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, U. States Frigate Chesapeake, Washington, 12 March 1807., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:42)
    He is sending up the Seamen for the Chesapeake.
  - Letter - Wm. H. Allen, Lieut., Philadelphia, to Capt. Charles Gordon, U.S.S. Chesapeake, City of Washington, 27 March 1807., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:43)
    Re: deserters from the newly assembled crew.
  - Letter - F. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, 4 May 1807., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:44)
    Re: attempted sale of James Barron's Dry Dock plan; news of Norfolk business interests.
  - Letter - Th[omas] Jefferson to Capt. James Barron, Hampton. 23 May 1807., 1 page. ALS,E. (Box-folder 1:45)
    Request that James Barron take an enclosed letter to Mr. Niggins at Malta and ask him to send back a pipe of Marsala Madeira if conveyance is available. Endorsement: "From that infamous Hypocrite, T. Jefferson" and "No consequence."
  - letter - James Barron, Hampton, to Colonel John Taylor, Washington, 19 April 1807., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:46)
    Re: the Arabian horse, Selim.
  - Letter - [James Barron], Hampton, to the Secretary of the Navy, 31 May 1807., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 1:47)
    Re: the conduct of James Cosgrove, who had been a gunman on the U.S.S. Essex: "most perverse."
  - Letter - Ro[bert] Saunders, [Williamsburg], to Commodore James Barron, Hampton, 10 June 1807., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:48)
    Letter by Mrs. Cole asking that her husband be released from service on the Chesapeake.
  - Letter - George McIntyre, Hampton, to Col. H.M. Clavering, Argyle F. Reg., 20 June 1807., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:49)
    A letter sent by Comm. Barron to Gibraltar (never delivered to Col. H.M.Clavering).
  - Items concerning the skirmish between the U.S.S. Chesapeake and the English warship Leopard and the Court of Enquiry that follow this event, 23 June 1807., 37 items. (Box-folder 1:50-82)
    Items in this subseries include: A description of the affair between the U.S.S. Chesaspeake commanded by Barron and the British warship Leopard, involving the brief skirmish and the capitulation of Barron; the request of Barron's officers for his arrest as a result of the capitulation; the passing of the command of Barron's ship to Capt. Stephen Decatur; the preparations for the Court Martial; the testimony; and the sentence of suspension. Opinions regarding the unfairness of the sentence are given by: B. Cocke of Washington; Robert Saunders, President of William and Mary College; and others.
    - Letter - "Officers of the late U.S. Ship Chesapeake," Hampton Roads, Ben Smith, W[illia]m Crane, W.H. Allen, J. Orde Creighton, Sidney Smith, and Sam[ue]l Brooke, to Rob[er]t Smith, Secretary of the U.S. Navy, Washington, 23 June 1807., 3 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 1:50)
      "Sensible of the disgrace... in the premature surrender of the U.S. Ship Chesapeake to the English Ship of Leopard... request that an order be issued for the arrest of Commander James Barron... ."
    - Cover letter - to Commodore James Barron from the Officers of the late U.S.S. Chesapeake at anchor in Hampton Roads, 23 June 1807., 1 page. ADS. (Box-folder 1:50)
    - Copy of letter - addressed to The Lieutenants and Sailing Master on board the Frigate Chesapeake by Comdr. J[ames] Barron, 23 June 1807., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 1:51)
      He (Comdr. James Barron) has forwarded a copy of the letter of accusations, as requested.
    - Copy of letter - of accusations sent by officers of the Chesapeake; letter of James Barron to R[ober]t Smith, Secretary of the Navy; and Abstract taken from the U.S. Frigate Chesapeake Log Book, 23 June 1807., 3 pages. ADrS. (Box-folder 1:52)
      An account of the half hour battle in which 3 men were killed and 16 wounded.
    - Copy of letter - from James Barron Frigate Chesapeake, Hampton Roads, to Rob[er]t Smith, Secretary of the Navy, Washington, 23 June 1807., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 1:53)
      Re: the letter sent by his officers and his inability to travel due to his wounds.
    - Copy of letter - from James Barron, U.S. Frigate Chesapeake, Chesapeake Bay, to Rob[er]t Smith, Secretary of the Navy, Washington, 23 June 1807., 2 pages. TCop. (Box-folder 1:54)
      Explaining the action between the Chesapeake and the English Warship Leopard.
    - Letter - Comm. James Barron to Lieut. Sidney Smith, 25 June 1807., 2 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 1:55)
      Re: divisions of cabins aboard ship.
    - Letter - R[ober]t Smith, Navy Department, to Ja[me]s Barron, Capt. in the Navy, Hampton, Virginia, 26 June 1807., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:56)
      Order to turn over command of the Frigate Chesapeake to Capt. Decatur.
    - Letter - [Commo. Samuel Barron] to [?], June 1807., 1 page. AL. (Box-folder 1:57)
      Re: information needed for the Court of Enquiry of the Affair of the Chesapeake and Leopard, involving his brother [James Barron].